<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A lamentation over thee O London with thy rulers and people who hast slighted the day of thy visitation and resisted the spirit of the Lord and despised His counsel ...</title>
            <author>R. C. (Richard Crane)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34917</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C6814</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28576</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10676633</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10676633</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45478</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34917)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45478)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1401:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A lamentation over thee O London with thy rulers and people who hast slighted the day of thy visitation and resisted the spirit of the Lord and despised His counsel ...</title>
                  <author>R. C. (Richard Crane)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>5 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: R.C.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends.</term>
               <term>London (England) --  Moral conditions.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45478:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45478:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A LAMENTATION Over thee O LONDON With thy RULERS and PEOPLE, who haſt ſlighted the day of thy Viſitation, and reſiſted the Spirit of the Lord, and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his counſel, and evil intreated and perſecuted his Servants, Meſſengers, and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren; and now muſt receive thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward at the hand of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Lord.</p>
            <q>
               <p>And when he was come neer, he beheld the City and wept over it, <bibl>Luke 19.41.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, thou that killeſt the Prophets and stoneſt them which are ſent unto thee, how of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten would I have gathered thy children together, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven as a hen gathereth her chickens under her wings, and ye would not? <bibl>Matth. 23.37.</bibl>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1665.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:45478:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45478:2"/>
            <head>A LAMENTATION Over thee O <hi>LONDON.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>O Thou great City, whoſe borders are even ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended beyond compaſs, and thy inhabitants like unto the mighty ſwelling of the ſea, even as it were numberleſſe, the day of thy judgment is come, and the ſword of the mighty God is drawn forth againſt thee, and he is come to plead the cauſe of his poor, oppreſſed, deſpiſed, and afflicted ones in thee whom thou haſt deſtinated for deſtruction, &amp; counted unworthy to live in thee, though the Lord, whoſe migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hand is ſtretched forth againſt thee, hath placed them there to live out the remnant of time given unto them, and thou ſeekeſt with thy utmoſt ſtrength, to root up what the Lord hath planted, and to ſeparate what he hath joyned together, and in what thou haſt done, thou haſt even done in deſpight of his love unto thee; O how hath he ſtriven and wreſtled with thee in the bowels of his dear love ſhed abroad in the hearts of his faithful lambs and ſervants for this many years paſt; O how hath the tender breathings of his love vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited thee, and thy Rulers, from year to year, and from time to time, and even from day to day, warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45478:3"/>
thee and thy Rulers of the day that is come, and hath overtaken thee, and thou haſt rewarded them, and art rewarding of them with priſons, whips, ſtocks, ſtones, and even with death, and now thou art filling up thy meaſure with baniſhment, which puniſhment is more ſevere then death it ſelf, and greedily art purſuing thy cruelty upon them by whole-ſale, not minding the ſword of Gods juſt judgment, which hath already pierced thy bowels; O thou City with thy inhabitants, that haſt made a mock and a ſcorne of the faithful warnings of the ſervants of the moſt high God, miniſtred and diſpenced in thee, early and late, in thy ſtreets, in thy Markets, and in many of thy dwellings, ſome being made ſigns unto thee, and others declaring in words the Mind of the Lord concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee, and in fulfilling the will of the Lord in true obedience, have delivered their meſſages unto thee even with their lives in their hands, in that day, the burden was theirs and they did bear it, and now it is thine, and thou muſt bear it, and though in times paſt thou haſt been threatned with Judgements of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other kind, yet haſt thou had thy God at hand, even thy riches and treaſure, and with it haſt ſtopped the wrath, which otherwiſe might have reached thee, and becauſe the mighty God hath permitted things ſo to work, thou haſt ſate as a Queen over the Nations, and haſt taſted no ſorrow, and for that end haſt thou mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified thy God, but haſt diſhonoured God Almighty, who is come to plead with thee in judgment, and now ſorrow ſhalt thou both feel and witneſſe, and he who is thy Judge will not at all be bribed, thy gold, thy ſilver, thy riches, and all thy coſtly delicates, will ſtand
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45478:3"/>
thee in no ſtead, unleſſe it be to adde plague unto plague, for Juſt is the Lord who is come to judge, and he will make inquiſition in thee, even in thee, O City for the innocent blood which hath been ſhed in our meetings, in your priſons, and on your pavements, and alſo for thoſe ſouls who have been moſt bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly thruſt out of their native land, into exile, their cries with their wives, &amp; tender children, are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the ears of the Lord God, and he hath regard unto them, and for their ſakes, yea even for their ſakes, is he entred into judgement with thee, O City and thy inhabitants, for thou mayſt obſerve that before thy rulers put forth their cruel hands to execute that barbarous penalty of baniſhment upon the people of the Lord, called Quakers, the judgement of the Lord which is now made viſible, was with-held, but as ſoon as they did make a preſident of their malice, the Lord did ſhew an example of his judgement, ye and not many doors<note n="*" place="margin">It was ſaid that in or neer <hi>Beerbinder</hi> lane, a meal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man were ſhut up of the Plague, who was <hi>E. B.</hi> his neer neighbor ſoon after he was baniſhed.</note> from the habitation of that faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſervant and Saint of the moſt high God <hi>Edward Bruſh,</hi> who with his dear Companion, <hi>James Hardin,</hi> was the firſt in <hi>England</hi> that the Lord permitted thy Rulers, O City, to wreak their wrath upon, yet this was not at all laid to heart, or taken notice of, but the ice being broke, or entry made, into this bloody work, ſeven more of the precious Lambs of the Lord, were moſt barbarouſly thruſt out of their native land into exile; and here was thy firſt aggravation, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this thing, and after them eight more for their precious teſtimony unto Gods dear truth thruſt out of the Nation in the like manner, and beſides thoſe num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers that are condemned by thy Rulers for baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45478:4"/>
now in that diſmal cell of <hi>Newgate,</hi> who for want of room and aire, many times, and my eyes with weeping tears have beheld them, panting even for breath through the grates of thy priſon, and all this thou layeſt not to heart, O City, neither thy Rulers, nor Inhabitants, but notwithſtanding the Lord is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into judgement with thee, and is giving thee a Cup which thou muſt drink, by ſending his Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger amongſt you, even his Plagues, which is that, which muſt and will awaken thee to receive thy reward; thou goeſt on ſtill, and does what in thee lies, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrate the deſtruction of them people, that never did, neither ſaid thee harme ever ſince they had a being, in that life which cannot reward or recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence evil with evil; but this in time thou muſt ſee and alſo confeſs.</p>
            <p>And though many may ſeek to ſave themſelves by flight from the Judgments come, &amp; coming; yet let ſuch know, though they mount upon dromadaries for haſt, the hand of God Almighty will overtake them, yea the ſtrong ſhall purſue the ſwift, and take hold on him, and to that end ſhall confeſſion be made by eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry tongue, that the Judgements of God are Juſt, and righteous, and that they are not come upon thee, O City, and thy Inhabitants at unawares, but many years warnings haſt thou had, yea thou haſt been warned near this twenty years by the ſervants of the moſt high, as aforeſaid, and know this, it is not only for thy groſſe unclean ſins, which thou haſt accumelated, which in theſe late years have ſo much abounded, but this is the ſweep of thy drag perſecution, yea <hi>PERSEC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>TION</hi> and the very malice of it, is that
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45478:4"/>
above all other, that doth awaken the wrath of God, and bring down vengeance upon a generation, this hath been known, this is known, and this will the Lord make thee know in time.</p>
            <p>And this may be ſaid of thee, O City, as of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> and a Lamentation taken up for thee, yea a bitter Lamentation; <hi>O that thou hadſt known in the day of thy viſitation, the things that belong to thy peace, but now are they hid from thy eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Woe is me for thee, O City, where is the man that ſhall ſtand in the gap, and make atonement unto the Lord, whoſe fierce wrath is kindled againſt thee, warnings thou haſt ſlighted, good Councel and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof from the Lord thou haſt rejected, the mercies and bleſſings of the Lord God thou haſt ſacrificed <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thy luſt, and haſt lived out of the ſence of him, who would have drawn thee unto himſelfe by the cords of love, as with the cords of a man, but thou haſt deſpiſed it, and now muſt thou eat the fruits of <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hy works; and this is thy portion from the Juſt <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and of the Lord.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
